ucas C.Wheeler, Ph

■ lucas.wheeler@colorado.edu | 🌴 https://lcwheeler.github.io/ | 🖸 lcwheeler | 💆 @LCWheeler9000

Research Interests

My research interests are focused on understanding the interactions between different biological scales. For example, how are genetic changes manifested at the biochemical and cellular levels and in turn at the level of organismal phenotypes and ecological effects? I aim to develop a research program that addresses these fundamental questions using plant secondary metabolism as a model system. I strive to use experiments, field studies, and computational modeling to develop a framework for unifying biological scales and understanding emergent properties of biological systems.

Research Experience

University of Colorado-Boulder

Jan 2018 – present

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCH

Boulder, CO

- · I am using transcriptomics, biochemistry, functional genetics, and bioinformatics to study the evolution of floral coloration in the Petunieae sub-family of Solanaceae.
- I have developed a computational approach for modeling the evolution of metabolic pathways and used it to simulate the evolution of the anthocyanin pigmentation pathway.

University of Oregon Sep 2012 - Dec 2017

GRADUATE RESEARCH

Eugene, OR

- · Designed an experiment that coupled ancestral sequence reconstruction with high-throughput binding experiments to study the evolution of target binding specificity in the S100 protein family.
- Studied the evolution of metal binding affinity and specificity in the S100 protein family using calorimetry and phylogenetics.

Montana State University

Sep 2009 - June 2012

UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH

Bozeman, MT

• Engineered virus-like particles containing various functional peptides including defensins and conotoxins, for biomedical applications.

Publications

Wheeler LC, Stacey SD (2019). Computational modeling of anthocyanin pathway evolution: Biases, hotspots, and trade-offs. Integrative and Comparative Biology.

Hiranmayi Duvvuri, Wheeler LC, Harms MJ (2018). pytc: open source python software for global analyses of isothermal titration calorimetry data. Biochemistry.

Wheeler LC, Anderson JA, Morrison AJ, Wong CE, Harms MJ (2017) Conservation of specificity intwo low-specificity proteins. Biochemistry.

Wheeler LC, Harms MJ (2017). S100A5 binds Ca2+ and Cu2+ independently. BMC Biophysics.

Wheeler LC, Donor MT, Prell JS, Harms MJ (2016). Multiple Evolutionary Origins of Ubiquitous Cu2+ and Zn2+ Binding in the S100 protein Family. PLoS ONE.

Wheeler LC, An-Lim S, Margusee S, Harms MJ (2016). The thermostability and specificity of ancient proteins. Current Opinions in Structural Biology.

Education

Ph.D. IN BIOCHEMISTRY

University of Oregon

Eugene, Oregon

Sep. 2012 - Dec. 2017

· Completed my PhD in the lab of Dr. Michael J. Harms

Montana State University

Bozeman, MT

B.S. IN BIOCHEMISTRY

Graduated with honors from Department of Chemistry and Biochemistry

FEBRUARY 14, 2020

LUCAS C WHEELER . CURRICULUM VITAE

Sep. 2009 - June 2012

Teaching Experience _____

2019	Floral Pigmentation Activity, Volunteer Instructor	Pinhead Institute
2018	Floral Pigmentation Lab & Lecture, Volunteer Instructor	CU Upward Bound
2013	Biochemistry Recitation, Instructor	University of Oregon
2013	Biochemistry Laboratory, Teaching assistant	University of Oregon
2012	General Chemistry Laboratory, Teaching assistant	University of Oregon

Honors & Awards

INTERNATIONAL

2015	Mechanisms of Protein Evolution III: Best Student Talk, Winner	Denver, CO
2015	Mechanisms of Protein Evolution III: Student Travel Award, Recipient	Denver, CO
2011-2012	Montana INBRE Research Award, Recipient	Bozeman, MT
2011	Geer-Howald-Callis & Swager Summer Research Awards, Recipient	Bozeman, MT

Strengths & Skills _____

Molecular Biology	Gene cloning, RNA/DNA extraction, preparation of NGS libraries, Virus-induced gene silencing		
Biochemistry/Biophysics	s Protein expression & purification, Isothermal Titration Calorimetry, Circular Dichroism Spectroscopy, HPLC		
Botanical Field Work	Plant collections, Preservation of tissues, Reflectance spectroscopy, Photography, Microscopy		
Scientific Programming	Python, R, Julia, Snakemake, Jupyter, Git & Github		
Bioinformatics Tools	Trinity, Salmon & Kallisto, Sleuth & DEseq2, BBtools, BWA, PhyML, RaxML, & ExaBayes		
Languages	English (native), Spanish (intermediate)		

Service & Outreach	
Citizens' Climate Lobby	Golden, CO
Volunteer	2018 - present
Quantitative Problem Solving & Research Communication Consortium	Eugene, OR
Co-chair	2016 - 2017
UO SafeRide Program	Eugene, OR
Volunteer	2018 - present
Mad Duck Science Fridays	Eugene, OR
VOLUNTEER	2013 - 2017
Associated Students of MSU	Bozeman, MT
STUDENT SENATOR	2010 - 2011
Undergraduate Chemistry Society	Bozeman, MT
Secretary & Vice-president	2009 - 2012
Sacaiawaa Middla School	Paraman MT
Sacajawea Middle School Volunteer Mentor	Bozeman, MT 2009-2010
lunin au Flancautam, Cabaal	D / OD
Juniper Elementary School	Bend, OR

VOLUNTEER MENTOR FOR STUDENTS WITH SPECIAL NEEDS

2005 - 2008

Conference Presentations

	Conference Presentations
Providence, R	Evolution meeting
June 2015	"Preferential fixation of structural or regulatory mutations depends on pathway position" Submitted talk
Tampa, Fl	Society for Integrative and Comparative Biology
Jan. 2015	"Computational modeling of anthocyanin pathway evolution" • Submitted talk
Austin, T	Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution
July 2011	"Phage display and deep sequencing to study the evolution of binding specificity" • Submitted talk
Bangalore, India	Third International Symposium on Protein Folding and Dynamics
Nov. 2016	"Tracing the evolution of peptide binding specificity in the \$100 protein family using phage display and deep sequencing" Submitted talk
Carbondale, II	Gibbs Conference on Biological Thermodynamics
Sep. 2016	"Preferential fixation of structural or regulatory mutations depends on pathway position" • Submitted talk
Denver, CC	Mechanisms of Protein Evolution III: Origins
Nov. 2015	"Tracing the evolutionary fluctuations of peptide binding specificity in the \$100 protein family" • Submitted talk
Carbondale, II	Gibbs Conference on Biological Thermodynamics
Sep. 2015	"Tracing the evolutionary fluctuations of peptide binding specificity in the \$100 protein family" • Submitted poster
Berkeley, CA	Protein Folding Consortium Workshop
May. 2015	"Probing the evolutionary history of peptide binding specificity in the \$100 protein family" • Submitted talk
Carbondale, II	Gibbs Conference on Biological Thermodynamics
Sep. 2014	"Evolutionary biophysical studies of peptide specificity in the S100s" • Submitted poster
Ann Arbor, M	Protein Folding Consortium Workshop
May. 2014	"Evolutionary biophysical studies of protein function in the \$100 family" • Submitted poster